Hello, and welcome back. I want to discuss now the Mumford-Shah
大家好 欢迎回来 今天我想讨论下 Mumford-Shah 图像分割技术
Image Segmentation technique, and I'm going to do that with one example.
我将借助一个例子来讲解这种技术
Let's just look at this image. We talk that image segmentation means
我们看看这些图像 当我们提到图像分割 这意味着
labeling the image. We want to label every segment that has
对图像进行标记 我们为每个有一定连贯性的分割段
some coherence in it with a different name, with a different number.
标记上不同的名字 不同的编号
One way of doing that is, of course, basically, painting that segment with a
当然 其中一种方法是
uniform, or a very smooth grey value. And that's the type of stuff that the
用一致或平滑过渡的灰度值 填充每个分割段
Mumford-Shah algorithm and technique tries to do.
而这正是 Mumford-Shah算法做的事情
Let's just discuss that. Here, we have an original image.
我们来探讨一下 这里有一幅原始图像
Don't pay attention to these two for the moment.
暂时不要管这两幅图
It's going to be very clear in just a few seconds.
过一会儿你就知道这两幅图的意义了
And this is the result of one implementation of Mumford-Shah image
这就是用 Mumford-Shah 图像分割技术实现的效果
segmentation. So, very rich gray values become just a
图像中非常丰富的灰度值变成了一些平滑的分割段
few smooth segments. Looks like almost like quantization when
这很像图像压缩中的量化
we talk about image compression. So, the first part is that we want to
所以 我们要做的第一步是
approximate the original image by just a few segments that are either constant or
用一些恒定灰度或平滑过渡的分割段 去近似原始图像
very smooth. Of course, we want an approximation.
当然 我们想要的是原图的近似
So, one of the terms that this Mumford-Shah needs to include is a
所以 Mumford-Shah算法需要包含的一项是
penalty from deviating too much from the original image.
对处理结果与原始图像之间偏差的约束
Of course, piece wise smooth, or piece wise constant, I could make this whole
当然 逐点平滑或逐点恒定可以将整个图像变得很白
image wide. So, that's one very smooth segment.
于是得到了一个非常平滑的分割段
But it's very far, if I do that, it would be very far from the original image.
但是这样一来 处理结果会和原始图像相差太大
So, one of the things is we have to somehow penalize for the difference
所以 我们必须以某种方法 约束两者之间的差距
between these two images. For example, the mean square error.
例如 使用均方误差
We already talk about it very early on in this class.
我们在前几周的视频中已经学过这个概念
So, one penalty is the mean square error. We want to get the piece wise smooth
所以 均方误差可以作为一种约束
version of this image, but not very far from it.
我们希望得到分段平滑的图像 但是不要和原图像差别太大
Now, you might wonder, okay, if you're going to penalize for the mean
现在 你也许会问 既然我们想降低均方误差
square error, why not to keep the image itself?
那为什么不保留原来的图像呢？
That's very clever, but we don't achieve any segmentation.
这个想法很聪明 不过 这样我们就没有对图像做任何分割
So, how do I know I don't achieve any segmentation?
那么 我怎么知道我没做任何分割？
Because I'm going to add a term that penalizes for having too many boundaries
对此 我要加入一个规定 就是对分割图像中过多的边界进行约束
in the segmented image. So, these are the regular edges of this
这些是这个图像的正常边缘
image. Very strong edges.
非常复杂的边缘
These are boundaries of the segments that we have here.
这些是这个结果中分割段的边界
I don't want to have too many. I don't want to have all these.
我不想要过多的边缘 不想保留所有这些边缘
I'm going to penalize for the number of edges for how many, how much do I pay for
我要约束边缘的数量 约束这些边界带来的代价
having boundaries. So that would be another term.
这是算法所包含的另一部分
I'm going to basically, on one hand, I want to penalize for very large
一方面 我需要约束偏差量
differences, and on the other hand, I'm going to penalize for edges.
另一方面 我需要约束边缘数
So, if you have too much edges, you are going to pay a price.
所以 如果图像中有过多的边缘 付出的代价也会更多
Bec, so, if I keep the image as it is, I have no error here but I have lot of
如果让图像保持原样 虽然没有误差 但是会有过多的边缘
edges. Basically, every pixel becomes a segment,
可以说是几乎每个像素都成为一个分割段
so I'm paying a very large penalty for edges.
那么 就要为大量的边缘付出很大的代价
If I have a flat image, I don't pay any penalty for edges, but I pay a very high
如果处理得到一个纯色图像 就不用为边缘付出任何代价
penalty for error. And then, I have to do a compromise
但是会为误差付出很大代价 所以 我们必须在这两种代价中
between these two and that's what Mumford-Shah basic concept is, to write
作一个折衷 这就是 Mumford-Shah 的基本思想
formulations that compromise between a representation of the image that is too
它将这种折衷公式化 避免结果与原图差别过大
far from the original image. We want to simplify representation not
我们希望简化图像 但同时与原图差别不太大
too far from the original image, and we also don't want to pay a high price and
我们也不想为分割出太多区域付出过多的代价
get too many segments. Now, there are many ways of doing this.
现在 有很多方法可以做到这些
There's some beautiful mathematical theory behind different formulations that
已经有很多优美的数学理论提出了不同的公式
do this compromise. Some theory relates even to compression.
来做这种折衷处理 有些理论甚至和压缩相关
You have to compress this image and this edges, and then you try to optimize for
你必须压缩这个图像和这些边缘 然后尽量优化
that, yours and my, need to compare for the
可能还需要对误差进行比较
error. And some very beautiful techniques with, in the framework of what's called
在变分方程和能量方程的框架中有一些优秀的技术
variation and formulations, and, energy formulations really, a lot of very
它们涉及到许多优秀的数学理论
beautiful mathematical theory, which actually relates to the mathematical
这些理论与下周将要讨论的
theory that we're going to be discussing next week when we talk about geometric
几何微分方程
differential equations and geometric varation of problems.
以及几何变分问题有关
But, here's the concept.
这里是概念
And very often in image processing, you have a concept and the multiple ways
我们经常见到 图像处理中的概念
of implementing that concept. And I want to make sure that you
有很多种实现方式
basically learn during this class, the concept behind Mumford-Shah.
我希望大家在课上学会Mumford-Shah的概念
I should also mention to you that this concept of approximation and penalty for
我还想提醒大家 近似的概念 以及对边缘数量的约束
too many edges applies also beyond image segmentation.
其应用远远超过图像分割领域
And people have extended the framework of Mumford-Shah type of formulations to
人们已经把类似Mumford-Shah模型中的公式扩展到
image registration and many, many other image and video processing problems.
图像配准以及很多其他图像和视频处理问题中去
Thank you very much. See you in the next video.
非常感谢大家 我们下个视频见 //果壳教育无边界字幕组 | wocow | luoyetx | 某音某莹